

General Information

Address: R. Luiz Oscar de Carvalho, 75, Florianópolis, Brazil.

Phone: +55 (48) 99150-3012. Email: pslucasps@gmail.com. Page: https://lucas.dev.br.

Summary

My journey working with Information Technology started back in 2006. From there until 2017 my major focus was in academia and research. Despite my dense involvement with academia, I also was involved in practical software development. Currently, I work as a Senior Engineer and my mission is to lead the Android and iOS development teams and to drive the product architecture.

During my academic formation, I had teaching experience with entry level programmers and undergraduate and graduate students. Teaching was crucial for me to develop mentoring skills, which benefits me as a software lead developer. These teaching abilities make me able to efficiently help and guide my team members to solve technical issues.

I have a deeper understanding of software development and practices. I have proficiency with a wide range of languages, such as Java, Kotlin, JavaScript, Swift, Python, and PHP and I can easily learn new languages, frameworks and tools. Furthermore, I am a well-experienced backend and frontend developer, being able to work with both, Web and mobile development. Moreover, I also have a higher ground knowledge and experience with essential software practices, such as testing, continuous integration and software architecture.

Education

Ph.D. student in Computer Science - Software Engineering.

Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Thesis: Automated Refactoring of Test Code, incomplete.

Master's degree in Computer Science - Software Engineering.

Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Dissertation: Reuse of Code and Execution of Test Fixture between Test Classes, 2016.

Bachelor's degree in Computer Science.

Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Course completion assignment: Webis: a Language and an Accessible Programming Environment, 2013.

Associate degree in Computer.

Federal Institute of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Course completion assignment: Computer Solutions, 2008.

Work Experience

2021 to present

Senior Engineer at Communication Security Group (CSG).

Android and iOS team lead; Responsible for driving the client product architecture; Continuous integration and continuous delivery using Bamboo pipelines; Android development with Java and Kotlin; iOS development with Swift and Objective-C; SQLite database.

2017 to 2021

System Analyst at Superintendency of Electronic Governance and Information and Communication Technology (SeTIC), Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Development and maintenance of software products used for internal procedures of the university; Redesign of servers infrastructure; Java Virtual Machine tuning for servers; Java development with Spring Boot and PrimeFaces; Sybase, Oracle, PostgreSQL and MySQL databases.

2020 to 2021

Development Manager of Course Monitoring and Evaluation System (SAAS) at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Development team manager; Product software architecture; Training of developers enrolled at the project; Continuous integration and continuous deployment using GitLab pipelines with Docker; JavaEE development with PrimeFaces; RESTful Web services implementation using Jersey; PostgreSQL database; Automated software testing with Selenium and JUnit.

2014 to 2021

Researcher at Software Engineering and Database Laboratory, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Research focused in software testing; Reuse of testing code; Reuse of testing code execution to reduce testing run time; Acceptance testing techniques.

2019 to 2020

Developer of the Judicialization System at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Application development using JHipster platform; Backend development with Node.js; Front-end development using Angular.

2018

Teacher of the Software Testing Training Course at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Automated software testing classes for IT employees of the university; Fundamentals principles of software testing; Unit testing with JUnit; System and acceptance testing using Selenium and Cucumber; Test Driven Development; Testing techniques such as parameterized tests, mocks and stubs; Testing design patterns; Test code smells.

2017

Teacher of the Software Testing Course at Vale do Itajaí University, Brazil.

Software testing classes for graduate students; Fundamentals principles of software testing; Unit testing with JUnit; System and acceptance testing using Selenium and Cucumber; Test Driven Development; Testing techniques such as parameterized tests, mocks and stubs; Testing design patterns; Test code smells.

2016 to 2017

Full-stack Developer at Britehouse, South Africa.

Development of short-time projects; Backend development using Node.js; Development of front-end applications using Angular.js and React.js frameworks; JavaScript and TypeScript development; MongoDB database.

2014 to 2015

Developer at Lepidus Tecnologia, Brazil.

JavaEE development; RESTful APIs development using Dropwizard; Front-end development with FreeMarker, Bootstrap and JavaScript; Plugin and CSS theme development for Open Journal Systems (OJS); CouchDB and MySQL databases.

2014 to 2018

Developer of Course Monitoring and Evaluation System (SAAS) at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

JavaEE development with PrimeFaces; RESTful Web services implementation using Jersey; PostgreSQL database; Automated software testing with Selenium and JUnit.

2012

Teacher of the Web Page Accessibility and Web Programming Training Course at Santa Catarina Association for Integration of the Blind, Brazil.

Web page accessibility and Web programming classes for people with visual impairment; HTML; CSS; Introduction to programming with PHP.

2011 to 2013

Scholarship Student of the Urban Bus Real-Time Information and Control System (SincroBus) Project at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Front-end development using Google Web Toolkit (GWT).

2011

Scholarship Student of the Social Integration in Visual Impaired Community Project at Educational Software Laboratory, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Responsible for the accessibility of Web pages; Text to speech synthesis using eSpeak and MBrola.

2010 to 2013

Intern at Education Software Laboratory, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2007 to 2008

Intern at Computer Laboratory, Federal Institute of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Computer Skills

- Object-oriented programming languages and design patterns.
- Software testing, Test-Driven Development and Behaviour-Driven Development.
- Agile software development practices
- Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery.
- Backend development
- Front-end Web development.
- Android development.
- iOS development.
- Design of RESTfull APIs
- Design of software architectures.

• Linux.

Publications

2021

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. *Estória: A Framework for Code and Execution Reuse between Test Classes*. Journal of Computer Science.

2021

Douglas Hiura Longo, Patrícia Vilain, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**. *Measuring Test Data Uniformity in Acceptance Tests for the FitNesse and Gherkin Notations*. Journal of Computer Science.

2020

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. LCCSS: *A Similarity Metric for Identifying Similar Test Code*. In: 14th Brazilian Symposium on Software Components, Architectures, and Reuse.

2019

Douglas Hiura Longo, Patrícia Vilain, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**. *Impacts of Data Uniformity in the Reuse of Acceptance Test Glue Code*. In: 31st International Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering.

2018

Beatriz Wilges, Douglas Hiura Longo, Gustavo Pereira Mateus, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**, Renato Cislaghi, Silvia Modesto Nassar, Almir dos Santos Albuquerque. *Quality Evaluation Processes of Courses Presented in a Results Management Module*. In: 11th International Conference of Education, Research and Innovation

2017

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. *Reuse of Fixture Setup between Test Classes*. In: 29th International Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering.

2016

Douglas Hiura Longo, Patrícia Vilain, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**, Ronaldo dos Santos Melo. *A Web Framework for Test Automation*. In: 18th International Conference on Information Integration and Web-based Applications and Services.

2016

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. *Execution and Code Reuse between Test Classes*. In: 14th International Conference on Software Engineering Research, Management and Applications.

2007

Lucas Pereira da Silva, Diego Rodrigo Vaz and Lucas Voigt. *Cybernetic Crimes at Colégio Agrícola de Camboriú*. In: 2nd Interdisciplinary Scientific and Technological Initiation Exhibition.

Awards

2020

3rd best paper award of the 14th Brazilian Symposium on Software Components, Architectures, and Reuse, Brazilian Conference on Software.

2014

Student Merit Award. Best graduate student of Computer Science, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.